const jsonData = [
    {
      "question": "Who wrote the text Hind Swaraj?",
      "options": [
        "Bal Gangadhar Tilak",
        "Jayaprakash Narayan",
        "Mahatma Gandhi",
        "Ram Mohan Roy"
      ],
      "answer": "Mahatma Gandhi"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who among the following argued about ‘Integrated Theory of  Evolution’?",
      "options": [
        "Sri Aurobindo",
        "M. K. Gandhi",
        "M.N. Roy",
        "B.R. Ambedkar"
      ],
      "answer": "Sri Aurobindo"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following texts was authored by B. R. Ambedkar?",
      "options": [
        "Annihilation of Caste",
        "Hind Swaraj",
        "The Life Divine",
        "Arthashastra"
      ],
      "answer": "Annihilation of Caste"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who wrote the text Reconstruction of Religious Thought in Islam?",
      "options": [
        "V.D.Savarkar",
        "Muhammad Iqbal",
        "Muhammad Ali Jinnah",
        "M.K.Gandhi"
      ],
      "answer": "Muhammad Iqbal"
    },
    {
      "question": "The High Caste Hindu Woman was written by",
      "options": [
        "Mahatma Gandhi",
        "Sri Aurobindo",
        "Pandita Ramabai",
        "Tarabai Shinde"
      ],
      "answer": "Pandita Ramabai"
    }
  ,



    {
      "question": "What are the distinctive features of modern Indian political thinkers?",
      "options": [
        "The ideas of modern Indian political thinkers are historically rooted in the context of colonialism.",
        "An amalgamation of political activism and theoretical reflection is peculiar to modern Indian political thinkers.",
        "Modern Indian political thinkers have unique metaphysical and epistemological questions that may substantially differ from the Western thinkers.",
        "All of these."
      ],
      "answer": "All of these."
    },
    {
      "question": "Raja Rammohan Roy was a vocal proponent of the freedom of the press. From the following, choose the one that was not among those grounds that he presented to the British Crown to relax press regulation in India.",
      "options": [
        "Press as a necessity for the sustainability and durability of British rule.",
        "Press as a grievance redressal mechanism.",
        "Press as a rightful platform for the revolutionary nationalist activities of Indians.",
        "Press as a means to keep a check on Christian missionaries who are meddling with the religious practices of natives."
      ],
      "answer": "Press as a rightful platform for the revolutionary nationalist activities of Indians."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following sentences is not correct regarding the interlinkages between political thought and political theory?",
      "options": [
        "Both political theory and political thought are concerned with the understanding of politics.",
        "Political thought is less systematic and generalized than political theory.",
        "To be considered as political theory, it should inevitably be developed in the West.",
        "Political thought is narrower in scope than political theory."
      ],
      "answer": "To be considered as political theory, it should inevitably be developed in the West."
    },
    {
      "question": "‘Mirat-ul-Akhbar’ was founded and edited by which of the following political thinkers?",
      "options": [
        "Abul Fazl",
        "Sheikh Mujibur Rahman",
        "Raja Rammohan Roy",
        "Muhammad Iqbal"
      ],
      "answer": "Raja Rammohan Roy"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is not correct regarding Raja Rammohan Roy’s approach to religion?",
      "options": [
        "Raja Rammohan Roy was a proponent of monotheism.",
        "Raja Rammohan Roy held that sacred religious texts should only be available for the orthodox Brahmins as making them publicly accessible could result in their misinterpretation.",
        "Raja Rammohan Roy opposed the monopoly of orthodox Brahmins over the sacred texts.",
        "Raja Rammohan Roy argued that religious associations could bring social and political transformations in society."
      ],
      "answer": "Raja Rammohan Roy held that sacred religious texts should only be available for the orthodox Brahmins as making them publicly accessible could result in their misinterpretation."
    },
    {
      "question": "“From India may come influences which will widen the horizons of Western political thinkers and which will give political ideas a sounder foundation of philosophical and metaphysical speculation.” -Which of the following scholars made the above statement?",
      "options": [
        "Norman D Palmer",
        "Shefali Jha",
        "Ramachandra Guha",
        "Anthony Parel"
      ],
      "answer": "Norman D Palmer"
    },
    {
      "question": "Raja Rammohan Roy was not influenced by which of the following events or ideas?",
      "options": [
        "French Revolution",
        "Freedom movement in Spain",
        "Cultural Revolution in China",
        "Freedom movement in Latin America"
      ],
      "answer": "Cultural Revolution in China"
    },
    {
      "question": "Why did Raja Rammohan Roy promote modern Western education?",
      "options": [
        "Raja Rammohan Roy promoted modern Western education due to its mere instrumentality for career advancements for the Indians.",
        "Raja Rammohan Roy considered modern Western education to be a medium for social transformation.",
        "Raja Rammohan Roy promoted modern Western education because he didn’t value Indian customs and traditions.",
        "None of these."
      ],
      "answer": "Raja Rammohan Roy considered modern Western education to be a medium for social transformation."
    },
    {
      "question": "On 5th April 1823, the colonial government issued an order restricting the freedom of the press in India. What was not among the grounds on which a publication could be restricted according to this order?",
      "options": [
        "Any publication that propagated native religions.",
        "Any publication that could threaten the peace, harmony and order in society.",
        "Any publication that could create suspicion and hatred among the Indians towards the colonial government.",
        "Any publication that was considered harmful and defamatory towards the royal family, government officials, and their allied powers."
      ],
      "answer": "Any publication that propagated native religions."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is not correct regarding Raja Rammohan Roy’s outlook towards the British rule?",
      "options": [
        "Raja Ram Mohan Roy thought that British rule would promote civil liberties.",
        "The only reason why Raja Rammohan Roy opposed the British rule was the denial of civil liberties to the Indians.",
        "Raja Ram Mohan Roy had chosen civil and religious liberty over political liberty.",
        "Raja Ram Mohan Roy considered that the natives of his period lacked the capacity for self-governance."
      ],
      "answer": "The only reason why Raja Rammohan Roy opposed the British rule was the denial of civil liberties to the Indians."
    }
  ,
    {
      "question": "On what grounds did Rabindranath Tagore oppose the Non-cooperation Movement?",
      "options": [
        "Rabindranath Tagore regarded the Non-cooperation Movement as being based on blind national pride.",
        "Rabindranath Tagore also argued that parochial anti-West tendencies within the Indian National Movement could hinder India’s relationship with the international community.",
        "Rabindranath Tagore was sceptical of Gandhiji’s call for boycotting foreign goods or clothes, based on the belief that Western textiles were impure. Tagore considered that as propagating untruths to sustain a political agitation.",
        "All of these."
      ],
      "answer": "All of these."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following sentences is not correct about Rabindranath’s views on the idea of man?",
      "options": [
        "Tagore was radical in his understanding of man and individual freedom.",
        "Tagore did not believe in the moral or ethical side of man.",
        "Tagore emphasised both the moral and the spiritual aspects of human nature.",
        "Tagore also spoke about the duality in human nature."
      ],
      "answer": "Tagore did not believe in the moral or ethical side of man."
    },
    {
      "question": "From the following statements, choose the one that is not correct regarding Rabindranath Tagore’s ideas on the East and the West.",
      "options": [
        "Rabindranath Tagore is known for his anti-West approach.",
        "Rabindranath Tagore advocated for a symbiosis of the East and the West.",
        "Rabindranath Tagore sought a deep association between the cultures of the East and the West.",
        "Rabindranath Tagore believed that a creative unity between the East and the West was only possible when the East had discovered its soul and identity for that reason."
      ],
      "answer": "Rabindranath Tagore is known for his anti-West approach."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is/are not correct regarding Rabindranath Tagore’s ideas on cosmopolitanism?",
      "options": [
        "Rabindranath Tagore considered all human beings as world citizens and argued that they owe their primary allegiance to the world community.",
        "Rabindranath Tagore argued that the motivation behind cosmopolitanism is based on an existential orientation- a way of being in this world.",
        "Rabindranath Tagore’s ideas on cosmopolitanism draws its justifications from theoretical abstractions devoid of any existential orientation.",
        "Rabindranath Tagore’s cosmopolitanism is partly a consequence of his philosophical and historiographical understanding that statist conceptions of history cannot totally capture social life."
      ],
      "answer": "Rabindranath Tagore’s ideas on cosmopolitanism draws its justifications from theoretical abstractions devoid of any existential orientation."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is not correct regarding Tagore’s views on the Zamindari system?",
      "options": [
        "Tagore argued that the zamindari system was for the benefit of the masses.",
        "Tagore believed that the zamindari system, which claimed to represent the people's interests, was flawed.",
        "As a practitioner of zamindari, Tagore could sense the cruelty associated with the zamindari system.",
        "Tagore was genuinely apologetic and embarrassed about the whole system of zamindari."
      ],
      "answer": "Tagore argued that the zamindari system was for the benefit of the masses."
    },
    {
      "question": "According to Rabindranath Tagore, what does the ‘Universal Man’ strive for?",
      "options": [
        "Happiness",
        "Necessities",
        "Magnificence",
        "Beauty"
      ],
      "answer": "Magnificence"
    },
    {
      "question": "What was Rabindranath Tagore’s position on the Charkha Programme?",
      "options": [
        "Rabindranath Tagore was apprehensive about the charkha and didn’t think that the mere burning of foreign clothes was a solution to India’s problems.",
        "The economic efficiency of the Charkha Programme was questionable for Rabindranath Tagore.",
        "Rabindranath Tagore was also skeptical of the use of moral language instead of economic language in the programme.",
        "All of these."
      ],
      "answer": "All of these."
    },
    {
      "question": "In response to which of the following events did Rabindranath Tagore renounce his Knighthood?",
      "options": [
        "Jallianwala Bagh Massacre",
        "Partition of India",
        "Non-Cooperation Movement",
        "The Holocaust"
      ],
      "answer": "Jallianwala Bagh Massacre"
    },
    {
      "question": "From the following sentences, choose the one that is not correct regarding Rabindranath Tagore’s ideas on nationalism.",
      "options": [
        "Tagore was an ardent nationalist of his time.",
        "Tagore viewed nationalism as the breeding ground for imperialism.",
        "Tagore viewed nationalism as a danger to humanity.",
        "Tagore argued that the obsession with nationalism could lead to war, hatred and mutual suspicion among the nations."
      ],
      "answer": "Tagore was an ardent nationalist of his time."
    },
    {
      "question": "Tagore can also be regarded as a rooted cosmopolitan thinker because-",
      "options": [
        "Tagore believed in the universal values of the East.",
        "Tagore respected the Indian tradition.",
        "Tagore respected various individual traditions and nationalities but also believed in universal values.",
        "Tagore believed in the universal values of the West."
      ],
      "answer": "Tagore respected various individual traditions and nationalities but also believed in universal values."
    }
  ,
    {
      "question": "The political thought of Aurobindo engages with-",
      "options": [
        "Only the political dimensions of human life.",
        "Only the spiritual dimensions of human life.",
        "Both the political and spiritual dimensions of human life.",
        "Neither the political nor the spiritual dimensions of human life."
      ],
      "answer": "Both the political and spiritual dimensions of human life."
    },
    {
      "question": "During the early phases of his life, Aurobindo actively participated in the national movement of India. During this time, his companionship is known with which of the following political leaders?",
      "options": [
        "Bipin Chandra Pal",
        "Bal Gangadhar Tilak",
        "Both Bipin Chandra Pal and Bal Gangadhar Tilak",
        "B.R. Ambedkar."
      ],
      "answer": "Both Bipin Chandra Pal and Bal Gangadhar Tilak"
    },
    {
      "question": "What does ‘True Self’ mean as articulated by Aurobindo?",
      "options": [
        "Rational mind",
        "Truthful self",
        "Spiritual individual",
        "Physical self"
      ],
      "answer": "Spiritual individual"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who founded the journal ‘Karmayogin’?",
      "options": [
        "Mahatma Gandhi",
        "Aurobindo",
        "Bal Gangadhar Tilak",
        "Jawaharlal Nehru"
      ],
      "answer": "Aurobindo"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following sentences is incorrect about Aurobindo’s views on Nationalism?",
      "options": [
        "Aurobindo had a religious conception of nationalism.",
        "Aurobindo believed that nationalism was a religion gifted by God and argued that God was immortal, and so was nationalism.",
        "Aurobindo viewed nationalism as a hindrance towards attaining human unity.",
        "Aurobindo argued that nationalism is not merely a political programme."
      ],
      "answer": "Aurobindo viewed nationalism as a hindrance towards attaining human unity."
    },
    {
      "question": "From the following statements, choose the one that is not correct regarding Aurobindo’s conceptualisation of a ‘spiritual religion of humanity’.",
      "options": [
        "A spiritual religion of humanity emphasises a universal religion for all human beings.",
        "A spiritual religion of humanity is considered as the means for universal human unity.",
        "A spiritual religion of humanity indicates the increasing realisation of a divine reality in which we are all one.",
        "Aurobindo advocates a spiritual religion of humanity because, in his view, spiritual foundation can lead to the psychological unification of people."
      ],
      "answer": "A spiritual religion of humanity emphasises a universal religion for all human beings."
    },
    {
      "question": "During the freedom movement in India, Aurobindo was associated with which one of the following?",
      "options": [
        "Moderate section of the Congress",
        "Extremist section of the Congress",
        "Indian National Army",
        "Muslim League"
      ],
      "answer": "Extremist section of the Congress"
    },
    {
      "question": "Read the following statements and choose the correct option from below-\n\nStatement I: Aurobindo talks about the ‘economics of a spiritualised society’, which intends to provide everyone with the pleasure of work in accordance with their nature and leisure as required for their inner development.\nStatement II: According to Aurobindo, the prime objective of that society is to ensure a stable machinery of production for a longer time.",
      "options": [
        "Only Statement-I is correct.",
        "Only Statement-II is correct.",
        "Both Statement-I & Statement-II are correct.",
        "Neither Statement-I nor Statement-II are correct."
      ],
      "answer": "Only Statement-I is correct."
    },
    {
      "question": "Rajas element denotes -",
      "options": [
        "A state of illumination",
        "A state of ignorance",
        "The will to action",
        "A state of luxury"
      ],
      "answer": "The will to action"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following sentences is not correct about Aurobindo’s views on the Gita?",
      "options": [
        "Aurobindo argued that the Gita should not be understood merely in its metaphysical connotations of ancient times.",
        "Aurobindo argued that the Gita should be understood in its renewed relevance to the living truths that it contains.",
        "Aurobindo believed that the Gita could not offer much in discovering the horizons of the future.",
        "Rather than focusing on the relevance of the Gita in understanding the past, Aurobindo’s approach towards it was more future-oriented."
      ],
      "answer": "Aurobindo believed that the Gita could not offer much in discovering the horizons of the future."
    }
  ,
    {
      "question": "In the first World's Parliament of Religions, held at the Art Institute of Chicago in 1893, Vivekananda delivered a profound speech that moved the attendees. What was his speech about?",
      "options": [
        "Universal education",
        "Universal tolerance",
        "Universal democracy",
        "Universal religion"
      ],
      "answer": "Universal tolerance"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following sentences is not correct about Vivekananda's views on the idea of freedom?",
      "options": [
        "Vivekananda believed that freedom was the key to a spiritual, social, and political life.",
        "Vivekananda opined that social and political liberty could be realized without paying attention to moral, ethical, and religious concerns.",
        "For Vivekananda, freedom was essential for an individual's social, political, or economic growth.",
        "Vivekananda considered that freedom is needed to maintain religious harmony and realize individual personality."
      ],
      "answer": "Vivekananda opined that social and political liberty could be realized without paying attention to moral, ethical, and religious concerns."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements accurately captures Vivekananda's views on politics and religion?",
      "options": [
        "Politics and religion are two different domains.",
        "Politics and religion are inseparable.",
        "Religion is only a manifestation of politics.",
        "Politics is dependent on religion."
      ],
      "answer": "Politics and religion are two different domains."
    },
    {
      "question": "From the statements below, choose the most accurate regarding the philosophy of 'Advaita Vedanta,' as propounded by Vivekananda.",
      "options": [
        "The philosophy of 'Advaita Vedanta' believes in the non-dualistic ultimate reality.",
        "The philosophy of 'Advaita Vedanta' aims to break down the existing privileges among people.",
        "In the philosophy of 'Advaita Vedanta,' man is considered no different from God, and it is held that human actions and thoughts should be guided by the principles of the divinity of the soul and the solidarity of mankind.",
        "All of these are correct."
      ],
      "answer": "All of these are correct."
    },
    {
      "question": "In the views of Vivekananda, which of the following was not among the three ways of tackling the existing social concerns in India?",
      "options": [
        "Emancipation of Women",
        "Positive Education",
        "Cultural Assimilation",
        "Upliftment of the Masses"
      ],
      "answer": "Cultural Assimilation"
    },
    {
      "question": "How did Vivekananda approach the colonial rule in India?",
      "options": [
        "Vivekananda held that the colonial rule had hypnotised the Indian mind and taken away its dignity and self-belief.",
        "Vivekananda defended the colonial rule on the grounds of its promotion of civil liberties.",
        "Although Vivekananda was apprehensive about colonial rule, he believed that bringing social legislation could ensure justice in that situation.",
        "Vivekananda was very skeptical of the West and opposed colonial rule for that very reason."
      ],
      "answer": "Vivekananda held that the colonial rule had hypnotised the Indian mind and taken away its dignity and self-belief."
    },
    {
      "question": "Who among the following was the spiritual guru of Vivekananda?",
      "options": [
        "Shri Ramakrishna Paramhans",
        "Mahatma Gandhi",
        "Raja Ram Mohan Roy",
        "Shankaracharya"
      ],
      "answer": "Shri Ramakrishna Paramhans"
    },
    {
      "question": "Read the following two statements and choose the correct option from below-\n\nStatement-I: Vivekananda believed in the Varnashrama system.\nStatement-II: Vivekananda criticised the Brahmanical practice of excluding the Shudras from accessing Vedic knowledge.",
      "options": [
        "Only Statement I is correct.",
        "Only Statement II is correct.",
        "Both Statements I and II are correct.",
        "Neither Statement I nor II is correct."
      ],
      "answer": "Both Statements I and II are correct."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements represents Vivekananda's thoughts on democracy?",
      "options": [
        "Vivekananda understood democracy as a process that inculcates faith, self-reliance, and self-government.",
        "For Vivekananda, democracy was equal to any form of direct rule.",
        "For Vivekananda, democracy was a mode of anarchy.",
        "By democracy, Vivekananda only referred to the indirect forms of representation."
      ],
      "answer": "Vivekananda understood democracy as a process that inculcates faith, self-reliance, and self-government."
    },
    {
      "question": "The compilation of the lectures given by Vivekananda in London was published as _________ .",
      "options": [
        "Karma Yoga",
        "Philosophical Vedanta",
        "Practical Vedanta",
        "A Memoir of London"
      ],
      "answer": "Practical Vedanta"
    }
  ,
    {
      "question": "Mahatma Gandhi started his political activism in which of the following countries?",
      "options": [
        "Sri Lanka",
        "South Africa",
        "Morocco",
        "Cuba"
      ],
      "answer": "South Africa"
    },
    {
      "question": "Mahatma Gandhi started his political activism in India with which of the following agitations?",
      "options": [
        "Quit India Movement",
        "Non-cooperation Movement",
        "Champaran Satyagraha",
        "Civil Disobedience Movement"
      ],
      "answer": "Champaran Satyagraha"
    },
    {
      "question": "Mahatma Gandhi was a voracious reader interested in writings from around the world. One of the major writings that greatly influenced him was ‘Life Without Principles’. Who among the following writers had authored this text?",
      "options": [
        "Henry David Thoreau",
        "Martin Luther King",
        "Nelson Mandela",
        "Ruskin Bond"
      ],
      "answer": "Henry David Thoreau"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to Mahatma Gandhi, which one among the following is not an ideal virtue of a Satyagrahi?",
      "options": [
        "Chastity",
        "Selfishness",
        "Truthfulness",
        "Fearlessness"
      ],
      "answer": "Selfishness"
    },
    {
      "question": "From the following statements, choose the one that is not correct regarding Mahatma Gandhi’s ideas on Satyagraha.",
      "options": [
        "Satyagraha, understood as the combination of two words- satya and agraha, implies the insistence on truth.",
        "Satyagraha is not merely a means of opposing authority, but it equally emphasises the practice of love and morality to strengthen society.",
        "Satyagraha relies on both violent and non-violent methods of opposition.",
        "Satyagraha relies on the self-suffering of the satyagrahi."
      ],
      "answer": "Satyagraha relies on both violent and non-violent methods of opposition."
    },
    {
      "question": "Read the following two statements and choose the correct option from below-\n\nStatement I: Mahatma Gandhi was sceptical of the uncontrolled madness behind the machinery. In his view, the usage of machinery should be guided by moral considerations regarding how men should conduct their lives.\nStatement II: Mahatma Gandhi also argued that the increasing use of technology and machinery could result in massive unemployment.",
      "options": [
        "Only Statement I is correct.",
        "Only Statement II is correct.",
        "Both Statement I & II are correct.",
        "Neither statement I nor II is correct."
      ],
      "answer": "Both Statement I & II are correct."
    },
    {
      "question": "Who classified the political philosophy of Mahatma Gandhi as 'Pax Gandhiana'?",
      "options": [
        "Ramchandra Guha",
        "Granville Austin",
        "Anthony J Parel",
        "V R Mehta"
      ],
      "answer": "Anthony J Parel"
    },
    {
      "question": "From the following statements, choose the one that is not correct regarding Mahatma Gandhi’s vision for future India.",
      "options": [
        "Mahatma Gandhi envisioned India as a spiritually enlightened society.",
        "Mahatma Gandhi argued that self-purification could bring spiritual emancipation and lead to a spiritually enlightened society.",
        "In the vision of Mahatma Gandhi, a spiritually enlightened society will be an egalitarian society.",
        "Mahatma Gandhi held that a centralised polity with modern technologies is a prerequisite for the existence of a spiritually enlightened society."
      ],
      "answer": "Mahatma Gandhi held that a centralised polity with modern technologies is a prerequisite for the existence of a spiritually enlightened society."
    },
    {
      "question": "According to Mahatma Gandhi, the European society was-",
      "options": [
        "A politically corrupt society",
        "A spiritual society",
        "A non-violent society",
        "An embodiment of social justice"
      ],
      "answer": "A politically corrupt society"
    },
    {
      "question": "On which of the following issues was there a significant disagreement between Mahatma Gandhi and B.R. Ambedkar?",
      "options": [
        "Swaraj",
        "Varnashrama Dharma",
        "Ahimsa",
        "Sarvodaya"
      ],
      "answer": "Varnashrama Dharma"
    }
  ,
    {
      "question": "Read the following two statements and choose the correct option from below-\n\nStatement-I: Muhammad Iqbal criticised the Indian National Congress as it was mostly dominated by the Hindus.\nStatement-II: However, Iqbal equally appreciated the secular outlook of the Indian National Congress towards politics and the state.",
      "options": [
        "Only Statement-I is correct.",
        "Only Statement-II is correct.",
        "Both Statements-I &II are correct.",
        "Neither Statement-I nor Statement II is correct."
      ],
      "answer": "Only Statement-I is correct."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following best describes the meaning of the term ‘Khudi’ as described by Iqbal?",
      "options": [
        "Respect",
        "Self-Affirmation or ego",
        "Ethics",
        "Morality"
      ],
      "answer": "Self-Affirmation or ego"
    },
    {
      "question": "In his book, ‘The Reconstruction of Religious Thought in Islam’, Iqbal emphasises the re-examination and reconstruction of the philosophy of Islam. From the following statements, choose the one that is not correct regarding Iqbal’s views on that matter.",
      "options": [
        "Iqbal’s emphasis on the need to reconstruct the philosophy of Islam originated in his understanding that Islam was experiencing a period of stagnation, which was leaving it behind other philosophical traditions.",
        "For such a reconstruction to be made possible, Iqbal argued, a sharp break from the past was more than necessary.",
        "Iqbal believed that modern knowledge, reason and democracy could lead to such reconstruction.",
        "Iqbal considered such reconstruction necessary because it could help men achieve moral perfection, thus leading to socio-economic transformation and justice."
      ],
      "answer": "For such a reconstruction to be made possible, Iqbal argued, a sharp break from the past was more than necessary."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following political organizations was Iqbal associated with?",
      "options": [
        "Justice Party",
        "Azad Hind Fauj",
        "Muslim League",
        "Hindu Mahasabha"
      ],
      "answer": "Muslim League"
    },
    {
      "question": "What was ‘Islam’ for Muhammad Iqbal?",
      "options": [
        "For Iqbal, Islam was a philosophy of life.",
        "For Iqbal, Islam was a way of living.",
        "For Iqbal, Islam was the embodiment of certain historical and cultural traditions and social and legal institutions.",
        "All of these."
      ],
      "answer": "All of these."
    },
    {
      "question": "From the following statements, choose the one that is not correct regarding Iqbal’s views on Sufism.",
      "options": [
        "Iqbal was very critical of the negative attitude of Sufism towards reason and rationalistic philosophy.",
        "Iqbal accepted the teachings of Sufism on the role of intuition in the process of cognition.",
        "Iqbal acknowledged that the mysticism of Sufism was essential for the overall development of human personality.",
        "Iqbal was also critical of Sufism’s preaching of men’s withdrawal from the real world."
      ],
      "answer": "Iqbal acknowledged that the mysticism of Sufism was essential for the overall development of human personality."
    },
    {
      "question": "Who among the following is considered the national poet of Pakistan?",
      "options": [
        "Mirza Galib",
        "Muhammad Iqbal",
        "Kaifi Azmi",
        "Akbar Allahabadi"
      ],
      "answer": "Muhammad Iqbal"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to Iqbal, what are the essential components of an ideal Muslim community?",
      "options": [
        "Only Homogeneity",
        "Only Unity",
        "Neither unity nor homogeneity",
        "Both the unity and homogeneity."
      ],
      "answer": "Both the unity and homogeneity."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following sentences is not correct regarding the religious and political thought of Muhammad Iqbal?",
      "options": [
        "Muhammad Iqbal emphasised the self and the human spirit.",
        "Muhammad Iqbal emphasised the capacity for self-determination.",
        "Muhammad Iqbal emphasised the self at the service of the divine.",
        "Muhammad Iqbal did not emphasise the self within a community."
      ],
      "answer": "Muhammad Iqbal did not emphasise the self within a community."
    },
    {
      "question": "Read the following two statements and choose the correct option from below-\n\nStatement I- Muhammad Iqbal tried to find a spiritual expression of anticolonialism in religion.\nStatement II- Through religion, Iqbal searched for an alternate path of development distinct from the West.",
      "options": [
        "Only Statement-I is correct.",
        "Only Statement-II is correct.",
        "Both Statements -I &II are correct.",
        "Neither Statement-I nor Statement II is correct."
      ],
      "answer": "Both Statements -I &II are correct."
    }
  ,
    {
      "question": "From the following political thinkers, choose the one who was not associated with the tradition of Hindu Nationalism.",
      "options": [
        "Bal Gangadhar Tilak",
        "Lala Lajpat Rai",
        "Jawaharlal Nehru",
        "V.D. Savarkar"
      ],
      "answer": "Jawaharlal Nehru"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is not correct regarding the social and political thought of Savarkar?",
      "options": [
        "Savarkar thought that only the fittest can survive the struggle of life while the others get eliminated eventually.",
        "Savarkar supported the principle of absolute non-violence.",
        "Savarkar believed in relative morality and argued that the morality of an action should be judged in accordance with the specificity of the action concerned.",
        "Savarkar believed that violence is natural to human society."
      ],
      "answer": "Savarkar supported the principle of absolute non-violence."
    },
    {
      "question": "The book ‘Life of Barrister Savarkar’ was written by",
      "options": [
        "M.S. Golwalkar",
        "V.D. Savarkar",
        "K.B. Hedgewar",
        "Nathuram Godse"
      ],
      "answer": "V.D. Savarkar"
    },
    {
      "question": "Read the following two statements and choose the correct option from below-\n\nI. Savarkar did not negate the right of minorities to co-exist, but he made it conditional on the ground of their acceptance of Hindu dominance.II. Savarkar supported preferential treatment to those minorities who accepted his condition of accepting the domination of Hindus.",
      "options": [
        "Only the statement (I) is correct.",
        "Only the statement (II) is correct.",
        "Both (I &II) statements are correct.",
        "Both (I & II) statements are incorrect."
      ],
      "answer": "Only the statement (I) is correct."
    },
    {
      "question": "According to V.D. Savarkar, which of the following terms can be the closest parallel to his philosophy of ‘Hindutva’?",
      "options": [
        "Hinduism",
        "Hinduness",
        "Hindi",
        "Hindustan"
      ],
      "answer": "Hinduness"
    },
    {
      "question": "From the following statements choose the one that is not correct regarding Savarkar’s views on the definition of ‘Hindu’.",
      "options": [
        "According to Savarkar, to be categorised as a Hindu, one must consider this land as both their fatherland as well as holy land.",
        "Savarkar minimised the significance of the religious criterion in the definition of a Hindu.",
        "Savarkar held that the religious criterion- that being a follower of Hinduism- was the most essential feature of defining a Hindu.",
        "Savarkar argued that Hindus were primarily the descendants of the Aryans."
      ],
      "answer": "Savarkar held that the religious criterion- that being a follower of Hinduism- was the most essential feature of defining a Hindu."
    },
    {
      "question": "According to Savarkar, which of the following Indian languages has the potential to preserve Hindu culture?",
      "options": [
        "Sanskrit",
        "Braj Bhasha",
        "Marathi",
        "Prakrit"
      ],
      "answer": "Sanskrit"
    },
    {
      "question": "From the following statements, choose the one that is not correct regarding Savarkar’s ideological differences with Mahatma Gandhi.",
      "options": [
        "In contrast to Gandhi, Savarkar advocated for science and rationality in the age of machines and technologies.",
        "Savarkar was more vocal against dogmatic religious practices than Gandhi.",
        "Savarkar was opposed to absolute non-violence, as propounded by Gandhi.",
        "Both Savarkar and Gandhi emphasised the practice of absolute non-violence in any political situation."
      ],
      "answer": "Both Savarkar and Gandhi emphasised the practice of absolute non-violence in any political situation."
    },
    {
      "question": "From the following statements, choose the one that is not correct regarding Savarkar’s ideas on nationalism.",
      "options": [
        "Savarkar viewed culture, religion, race, and historical affinity as contributors to the formation of nations.",
        "Savarkar’s ideas on nationalism were a synthesis of territorial nationalism offered by Congress and cultural-religious nationalism put forward by the Muslim League.",
        "Savarkar argued that, in the formation of a national unit, territorial unity had a bigger role to play than religious, racial or cultural attributes.",
        "Savarkar regarded one language and one culture (ek bhasha ek sanskriti) as the basis of the formation of modern nations."
      ],
      "answer": "Savarkar argued that, in the formation of a national unit, territorial unity had a bigger role to play than religious, racial or cultural attributes."
    },
    {
      "question": "Who among the following inspired V D Savarkar’s ideas on nation and nationalism?",
      "options": [
        "Vivekananda",
        "Mazzini",
        "Mahatma Gandhi",
        "Ernest Renan"
      ],
      "answer": "Mazzini"
    }
  ,
    {
      "question": "Which of the following sentences is incorrect regarding Jawaharlal Nehru’s vision of Indian Nationalism?",
      "options": [
        "Jawaharlal Nehru envisioned Indian nationalism to be secular.",
        "Jawaharlal Nehru envisioned Indian nationalism to be rational.",
        "Jawaharlal Nehru envisioned Indian nationalism to be guided by the principles of Hinduism.",
        "Jawaharlal Nehru envisioned Indian nationalism to be international in its outlook."
      ],
      "answer": "Jawaharlal Nehru envisioned Indian nationalism to be guided by the principles of Hinduism."
    },
    {
      "question": "In which of the following sessions Congress passed a Resolution on 'Fundamental Rights and Economic and Social Change'?",
      "options": [
        "Karachi Session of 1931",
        "Kanpur Session of 1925",
        "Nagpur Session of 1920",
        "Madras Session of 1927"
      ],
      "answer": "Karachi Session of 1931"
    },
    {
      "question": "Read the following two statements and choose the correct option from below-\nStatement-I: In his initial years, Jawaharlal Nehru favoured the radical politics of extremists like that of Bal Gangadhar Tilak.\nStatement-II: Nehru particularly admired the religious underpinnings of the extremists in that period.",
      "options": [
        "Only Statement-I is correct.",
        "Only Statement-II is correct.",
        "Both Statement-I &II are correct.",
        "Neither Statement-I nor Statement-II is correct."
      ],
      "answer": "Only Statement-I is correct."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following sentences is incorrect regarding Nehru's views on socialism?",
      "options": [
        "Nehru considered socialism as the most appropriate way of reducing poverty in India.",
        "Nehru added a moral concern to the idea of socialism.",
        "Nehru held that democracy and socialism are complementary to each other.",
        "Despite his inclination towards socialism, Nehru didn’t advocate for the Indian state to adopt socialist principles."
      ],
      "answer": "Despite his inclination towards socialism, Nehru didn’t advocate for the Indian state to adopt socialist principles."
    },
    {
      "question": "The monumental speech that Nehru delivered on the eve of India’s independence is known as-",
      "options": [
        "The Future of India",
        "My Vision for India",
        "Tryst with Destiny",
        "Swaraj is my Birth Right"
      ],
      "answer": "Tryst with Destiny"
    },
    {
      "question": "How did Jawaharlal Nehru approach the doctrine of secularism?",
      "options": [
        "For Nehru, secularism was not merely a political doctrine but also a social one.",
        "For Nehru, secularism meant a social structure wherein individuals would not be subjected to any hierarchy based on their religion.",
        "Nehru also held that, in secularism, inter-group and inter-personal relations would not be adversely affected by religious considerations.",
        "All of these."
      ],
      "answer": "All of these."
    },
    {
      "question": "Read the following two statements and choose the correct option from below-\nStatement-I: Nehru had a broader understanding of democracy, emphasising its social and economic dimensions.\nStatement-II: Nehru also held that it is only with the presence of equality that democracy can be sustained.",
      "options": [
        "Only Statement-I is correct.",
        "Only Statement-II is correct.",
        "Both Statement- I & II are correct.",
        "Neither Statement-I nor Statement-II is correct."
      ],
      "answer": "Both Statement- I & II are correct."
    },
    {
      "question": "Jawaharlal Nehru is known for his secularist outlook towards politics. He focused on how a secular state should act in a society marked with religious diversity. From the following statements, choose the one that is incorrect regarding his ideas on the functions of a secular state in a religiously diverse society.",
      "options": [
        "It is the duty of the secular state to protect religious diversity.",
        "A secular state should be committed to the rights of the minorities.",
        "Inter-religious domination is a natural consequence of a religiously diverse society, and it can be resolved spontaneously. Under no circumstances should a secular state intervene in the mutual affairs among existing religious communities.",
        "A secular state should intervene in the majoritarian acts of a religious community in order to undermine inter-religious domination."
      ],
      "answer": "Inter-religious domination is a natural consequence of a religiously diverse society, and it can be resolved spontaneously. Under no circumstances should a secular state intervene in the mutual affairs among existing religious communities."
    },
    {
      "question": "Read the following two statements on Gandhi and Nehru's vision of state and economic development, and choose the correct option from below-\n\nStatement-I: Gandhi and Nehru were unanimous on their idea of the state as a soulless machine and stated that it could hardly achieve any substantive development for the people.\nStatement-II: While Gandhi supported decentralization and small-scale industries, Nehru, on the other hand, was an advocate of centralized and planned economic development.",
      "options": [
        "Only Statement-I is correct.",
        "Only Statement-II is correct.",
        "Both Statement- I & II are correct.",
        "Neither Statement-I nor Statement-II is correct."
      ],
      "answer": "Only Statement-II is correct."
    },
    {
      "question": "Nehru was the founding editor of which of the following newspapers?",
      "options": [
        "Times of India",
        "The Hindu",
        "National Herald",
        "Dainik Bhaskar"
      ],
      "answer": "National Herald"
    }
  ,
    {
      "question": "From the following ideologies, choose the one that Jawaharlal Nehru did not associate with.",
      "options": [
        "Socialism",
        "Internationalism",
        "Imperialism",
        "Nationalism"
      ],
      "answer": "Imperialism"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Mahad Satyagraha in 1927, led by B R Ambedkar, mainly aimed at",
      "options": [
        "Asserting the right to access public tanks and wells by the untouchables.",
        "Securing voting rights for the Mahad caste.",
        "Attaining a separate electorate for the Dalits",
        "Propagating the ideals of Gandhian satyagraha among members of the Mahad caste."
      ],
      "answer": "Asserting the right to access public tanks and wells by the untouchables."
    },
    {
      "question": "From the given statements, choose the one that is not correct regarding Nehru’s overall conception of foreign policy.",
      "options": [
        "Nehru viewed that a country’s foreign policy should promote international peace and security.",
        "Nehru viewed that a country’s foreign policy should aim to maintain just and honourable relations between nations.",
        "Nehru viewed that a country’s foreign policy should be respectful towards international laws and treaties.",
        "Nehru believed that a country’s foreign policy should be guided solely by national interests."
      ],
      "answer": "Nehru believed that a country’s foreign policy should be guided solely by national interests."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements is incorrect regarding Nehru’s views on nationalism and internationalism?",
      "options": [
        "Nehru believed that nationalism and internationalism could co-exist.",
        "Nehru considered cooperation among the nations necessary for their survival and progress.",
        "Nehru advocated eliminating war as it creates an environment of mutual hatred and fear",
        "Nehru was a vocal critic of the idea of nation and nationalism."
      ],
      "answer": "Nehru was a vocal critic of the idea of nation and nationalism."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following political parties was founded by B R Ambedkar?",
      "options": [
        "Swatantra Party",
        "Praja Socialist Party",
        "Independent Labour Party",
        "Bahujan Samaj Party"
      ],
      "answer": "Independent Labour Party"
    },
    {
      "question": "Read the following two statements and choose the correct option from below-\nStatement-I: Ambedkar argued that caste was the major hindrance towards the formation of a united political community in India.\nStatement-II: The caste system, Ambedkar argued, maintained its hierarchies primarily by voluntary submissions of people characterised by ‘an ascending scale of reverence and a descending scale of contempt’.",
      "options": [
        "Only Statement-I is correct.",
        "Only Statement-II is correct.",
        "Both Statement-I &II are correct.",
        "Neither Statement-I nor Statement-II is correct."
      ],
      "answer": "Both Statement-I &II are correct."
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1924, Ambedkar founded the Bahishkrit Hitakarini Sabha (Group for the Wellbeing of the Excluded). From the following sentences, choose the one that is not correct regarding the same.",
      "options": [
        "Bahishkrit Hitakarini Sabha was an embodiment of Ambedkar’s intensive campaign for social reform",
        "Bahishkrit Hitakarini Sabha was primarily formed to participate in electoral politics.",
        "Bahishkrit Hitakarini Sabha was formed to promote socio-political awareness among the Dalits.",
        "Bahishkrit Hitakarini Sabha also aimed to raise public awareness about the grievances faced by the Dalits."
      ],
      "answer": "Bahishkrit Hitakarini Sabha was primarily formed to participate in electoral politics."
    },
    {
      "question": "From the following statements, choose the correct one regarding Ambedkar’s criticism of the caste system.",
      "options": [
        "Ambedkar held that caste had killed the public spirit in India.",
        "Ambedkar held that caste had destroyed the sense of public charity in India.",
        "Ambedkar held that caste had made public opinion impossible in India.",
        "All of these."
      ],
      "answer": "All of these."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following was not one among the five tenets of the Panchsheel Agreement as signed in 1954?",
      "options": [
        "Peaceful co-existence.",
        "Respect towards each other’s sovereignty and territorial integrity.",
        "Non-interference in each other’s domestic matters.",
        "Mediation by a third party during conflict."
      ],
      "answer": "Mediation by a third party during conflict."
    },
    {
      "question": "Who among the following is the author of Foreign Elements in the Hindu Population?",
      "options": [
        "B R Ambedkar",
        "Jawaharlal Nehru",
        "D R Bhandarkar",
        "V D Savarkar"
      ],
      "answer": "D R Bhandarkar"
    }
  ,
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements is incorrect regarding Ambedkar's understanding of democracy?",
      "options": [
        "For Ambedkar, democracy is the means and ends of forming an ideal society.",
        "Ambedkar argued that scientific outlook and rationality are not necessarily linked to the practice of democracy.",
        "In Ambedkar’s view, democracy is not merely a form of government but also a mode of associated living where everybody is treated with respect.",
        "Ambedkar envisioned democracy as a medium of social transformation and human progress."
      ],
      "answer": "Ambedkar argued that scientific outlook and rationality are not necessarily linked to the practice of democracy."
    },
    {
      "question": "What is Ramabai’s idea of true religion?",
      "options": [
        "Religion is about following sacred scriptures, and the priestly class",
        "Ancient Hinduism is the true religion",
        "Christianity is the true religion",
        "Religion is about acting according to one’s conscience"
      ],
      "answer": "Religion is about acting according to one’s conscience"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to Ambedkar, which of the following institutions was the representative of the modern forms of parliamentary democracy in India?",
      "options": [
        "Buddhist Sanghas",
        "Mughal Durbars",
        "Islamic Madrasas",
        "Khap Panchayats."
      ],
      "answer": "Buddhist Sanghas"
    },
    {
      "question": "“A democratic form of government presupposes a democratic form of a society; the formal framework of democracy is of no value and would indeed be a misfit if there was no social democracy”. -The above statement was made by",
      "options": [
        "Jawaharlal Nehru",
        "Pandita Ramabai",
        "B.R. Ambedkar",
        "Mahatma Gandhi"
      ],
      "answer": "B.R. Ambedkar"
    },
    {
      "question": "Pandita Ramabai is known as a devoted champion of women’s rights in India. From the following statements, choose the one that most adequately explains her approach towards women’s emancipation.",
      "options": [
        "Ramabai argued that the emancipation of women was possible through social reforms.",
        "Ramabai argued that the emancipation of women could be brought about through education.",
        "Ramabai’s vision for women’s emancipation was not limited to social reform and education alone. Liberating women through self-reliance was another essential aspect of women’s emancipation for Ramabai.",
        "Ramabai held that it was only through Western liberal education that women could be emancipated."
      ],
      "answer": "Ramabai’s vision for women’s emancipation was not limited to social reform and education alone. Liberating women through self-reliance was another essential aspect of women’s emancipation for Ramabai."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following institutions was not founded by Ramabai?",
      "options": [
        "Arya Mahila Samaj",
        "Mukti Sadan",
        "Sharda Sadan",
        "Seva Sadan"
      ],
      "answer": "Seva Sadan"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who among the following regarded Ramabai's conversion to Christianity as a radical act that challenged the upper caste Hindu patriarchal system?",
      "options": [
        "Kanshi Ram",
        "B.R. Ambedkar",
        "Jyotirao Phule",
        "Bal Gangadhar Tilak"
      ],
      "answer": "Jyotirao Phule"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following, according to Ambedkar, is crucial for preserving and strengthening democracy in India?",
      "options": [
        "Embracing extra-constitutional methods in politics",
        "Fostering hero-worship of leaders",
        "Upholding political democracy alongside social and economic democracy",
        "None of these."
      ],
      "answer": "Upholding political democracy alongside social and economic democracy"
    },
    {
      "question": "During the pilgrimages that Ramabai undertook during her childhood with her parents, she had the opportunity to learn many languages. Which among the following was not one of those?",
      "options": [
        "Marathi",
        "Bengali",
        "Hindustani",
        "Kannada"
      ],
      "answer": "Bengali"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is not an element of constitutional morality?",
      "options": [
        "Freedom and self-restraint.",
        "Recognition of plurality.",
        "Being sceptical of any personification of authority.",
        "Right to violent protest when necessary."
      ],
      "answer": "Right to violent protest when necessary."
    }
  ,
    {
      "question": "From the following statements, choose the one that is not correct regarding Ramabai’s ideas as explicated in her book ‘Stri Dharma Niti’.",
      "options": [
        "In ‘Stri Dharma Niti’, Ramabai advised the wife not to disobey her husband.",
        "In ‘Stri Dharma Niti’, Ramabai presumed that domestic works were the primary responsibility of women.",
        "In ‘Stri Dharma Niti’, Ramabai supported child marriage.",
        "In ‘Stri Dharma Niti’, Ramabai supported marriage after attaining an appropriate age."
      ],
      "answer": "In ‘Stri Dharma Niti’, Ramabai supported child marriage."
    },
    {
      "question": "Ram Manohar Lohia is known as-",
      "options": [
        "A socialist thinker",
        "A capitalist thinker",
        "A spiritual thinker",
        "A communist thinker"
      ],
      "answer": "A socialist thinker"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to Yogendra Yadav, what was not among the three ‘sins’ that Lohia committed which ultimately led to the absence of Lohia’s ideals in the public political discourse in India after his death?",
      "options": [
        "Lohia’s personal attack on Nehru in a period when the latter was considered God-like.",
        "Lohia’s campaign against English.",
        "Lohia’s campaign against Hindi.",
        "Lohia’s questioning of upper-caste dominance."
      ],
      "answer": "Lohia’s campaign against Hindi."
    },
    {
      "question": "Read the following two statements and choose the correct option from below-\n\nStatement-I: Ramabai argued that neither the male members from their own race nor any female teacher from a foreign land was appropriate for educating Indian women. \n\nStatement-II: Ramabai argued that the diffusion of knowledge should come from within, and native women teachers were more suitable for that task.",
      "options": [
        "Only Statement-I is correct.",
        "Only Statement-II is correct.",
        "Both Statement-I &II are correct.",
        "Neither Statement-I nor Statement-II is correct."
      ],
      "answer": "Both Statement-I &II are correct."
    },
    {
      "question": "In her autobiographical account, A Testimony of Our Inexhaustible Treasure, Ramabai had a critical outlook towards the Hindu Dharma Shastras. She particularly stated that all Hindu scriptures exhibited one feature in common: the marginalisation of women and ___________.",
      "options": [
        "Marginalisation of the Kshatriyas",
        "Marginalisation of the lower castes",
        "Marginalisation of the transgender community",
        "Marginalisation of the non-Aryans."
      ],
      "answer": "Marginalisation of the lower castes"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to Ramabai, what were the presumed beliefs which led to the unwantedness of a girl child in India?",
      "options": [
        "It was presumed that a girl child was the property of someone else.",
        "It was presumed that a girl child would be of no use to her parents in their old age.",
        "It was presumed that it was only through the male child that salvation could be attained.",
        "All of these."
      ],
      "answer": "All of these."
    },
    {
      "question": "On the questions of caste and modernity, which among the following thinkers can be regarded as a bridge between Gandhi and Ambedkar?",
      "options": [
        "Pandita Ramabai",
        "Jawaharlal Nehru",
        "Jyotiba Phule",
        "Ram Manohar Lohia"
      ],
      "answer": "Ram Manohar Lohia"
    },
    {
      "question": "Read the following two statements and choose the correct option from below-\n\nStatement-I: Ramabai argued that Indian women had a better status in the past in comparison to her contemporary degradation.\nStatement-II: Ramabai explains this degradation in the status of women in terms of the degradation of the Hindu nation.",
      "options": [
        "Only Statement-I is correct.",
        "Only Statement-II is correct.",
        "Both Statement-I &II are correct.",
        "Neither Statement-I nor Statement-II is correct."
      ],
      "answer": "Both Statement-I &II are correct."
    },
    {
      "question": "From the following statements, choose the one that is not correct regarding Lohia’s ‘principle of immediacy’.",
      "options": [
        "Each action has an ethical justification intrinsic to itself.",
        "The ethical justification of each action is based on the present and not on the distant future.",
        "The principle of immediacy would save people from the politics of greed or fear.",
        "Human actions can only be justified in relation to their future implications, not their present ramifications."
      ],
      "answer": "Human actions can only be justified in relation to their future implications, not their present ramifications."
    },
    {
      "question": "According to Ramabai, which among the following stages of the life of a high-caste Hindu woman can be considered the most dreadful period for her?",
      "options": [
        "Childhood",
        "Adolescence",
        "Widowhood/Old Age",
        "Married Life"
      ],
      "answer": "Widowhood/Old Age"
    }
  ,
    {
      "question": "Ram Manohar Lohia’s approach towards understanding social stratifications and inequality can be termed as-",
      "options": [
        "A class-based approach",
        "A linguistic approach",
        "An intersectional approach",
        "A gender-based approach"
      ],
      "answer": "An intersectional approach"
    },
    {
      "question": "Despite agreeing with Periyar on many political aspects, Ram Manohar Lohia also differed from him on certain occasions. What is not correct regarding Lohia’s disagreements with Periyar?",
      "options": [
        "Lohia differed from Periyar on the issues of violent anti-Brahmanism.",
        "Lohia differed from Periyar in the latter’s campaigns against Gandhi.",
        "Lohia differed from Periyar in the latter’s campaigns against Hindi.",
        "Lohia differed from Periyar on the need to annihilate caste."
      ],
      "answer": "Lohia differed from Periyar on the need to annihilate caste."
    },
    {
      "question": "From the following statements, choose the one that is not correct regarding Lohia’s views on the reservation system.",
      "options": [
        "Lohia was a major proponent of the reservation system in India as he thought that it would enable the entry of the marginalised sections of society into public life and administration.",
        "Lohia viewed that reservation was a means to secure selfish and individualistic objectives.",
        "Lohia viewed reservation as a means to bring social equality.",
        "Lohia also viewed that reservation could act towards the enhancement of national prosperity."
      ],
      "answer": "Lohia viewed that reservation was a means to secure selfish and individualistic objectives."
    },
    {
      "question": "From the following statements, choose the one that is not correct regarding Lohia’s approach towards the caste system.",
      "options": [
        "Lohia regarded caste as both a discriminating social structure’ and a disabling cultural phenomenon’.",
        "Lohia argued that caste had a uniform mode of operation across the country.",
        "Lohia argued that the destruction of the caste system was not an easy task and required a multi-sided attack on the political, historical, philosophical and economic roots of the system.",
        "Lohia argued that in its form and operation, caste exhibited region-specific variations in the country."
      ],
      "answer": "Lohia argued that caste had a uniform mode of operation across the country."
    },
    {
      "question": "Read the following two statements and choose the correct option given below-\n\nStatement I:  Lohia was a prominent leader of the ‘Angrezi Hatao Movement’, and he advocated the replacement of English with the Hindi language as the lingua franca of India. \n\nStatement II: Lohia opposed English not because it was a foreign language but because it was, in the Indian context, a vehicle of inequality and social exclusion.",
      "options": [
        "Only Statement I is correct.",
        "Only Statement II is correct.",
        "Both Statements I &II are correct.",
        "Neither Statement I nor Statement II is correct."
      ],
      "answer": "Both Statements I &II are correct."
    },
    {
      "question": "The book entitled ‘Marx, Gandhi and Socialism’ was authored by which of the following political thinkers?",
      "options": [
        "B.R. Ambedkar",
        "Ram Manohar Lohia",
        "M.N. Roy",
        "Jayaprakash Narayan"
      ],
      "answer": "Ram Manohar Lohia"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is/are not among the four key areas that Lohia considered important to root out the double oppression of the women of depressed castes?",
      "options": [
        "Re-examination of the institution of marriage and the hypocrisies involved.",
        "Equality in educational and property rights.",
        "Preferential treatment in politics and employment.",
        "Educating women on performing their duties as ideal wives and mothers."
      ],
      "answer": "Educating women on performing their duties as ideal wives and mothers."
    },
    {
      "question": "According to Lohia, the Indian ruling caste had three distinctive features. What was not one among those?",
      "options": [
        "English education",
        "Wealth",
        "Religion",
        "High caste"
      ],
      "answer": "Religion"
    },
    {
      "question": "What was/were not included in Lohia’s ‘Sapt Kranti’ (Seven Revolutions)?",
      "options": [
        "Satyagraha",
        "Destruction of castes",
        "Protection of private property",
        "Equality between men and women"
      ],
      "answer": "Protection of private property"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who among the following had proposed the idea of Chaukhambha Raj (Four Pillar States) that included: village, district, province, and center?",
      "options": [
        "Jayaprakash Narayan",
        "Rammanohar Lohia",
        "Jawaharlal Nehru",
        "Madan Mohan Malviya"
      ],
      "answer": "Rammanohar Lohia"
    }
  ,
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following book is written by Mahatma Gandhi?",
      "options": [
        "Hind Swaraj",
        "Discovery of India",
        "Gitanjali",
        "Ghare Baire"
      ],
      "answer": "Hind Swaraj"
    },
    {
      "question": "Mahatma Gandhi started his political activism in India with which of the following agitations?",
      "options": [
        "Salt satyagraha or Dandi March",
        "Champaran satyagraha 1917",
        "Non-cooperation movement",
        "Civil Disobedience movement"
      ],
      "answer": "Champaran satyagraha 1917"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following sentences is not correct about the concept of Satyagraha?",
      "options": [
        "For Gandhiji, Satyagraha consists of two words Satya and Agraha",
        "These terms together implies the insistence on truth, that truth is ultimate and it is absolute",
        "It emphasizes that our experience of truth may vary but the truth shall finally triumph",
        "The method for arriving or understanding satya or truth is through violence"
      ],
      "answer": "The method for arriving or understanding satya or truth is through violence"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following is not the correct virtue of a Satyagrah?",
      "options": [
        "Brahmacharya",
        "Truthfulness or satya",
        "Greed",
        "Fearlessness"
      ],
      "answer": "Greed"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following sentences is not correct about the concept of Swaraj?",
      "options": [
        "Swaraj can be attained only through means of non-violence",
        "Swaraj is not self-government or the quest for home rule.",
        "Swaraj as self-rule in one's own self and the quest for self-improvement.",
        "Gandhi wrote about swaraj in his text Hind Swaraj"
      ],
      "answer": "Swaraj is not self-government or the quest for home rule."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following was not supported by Mahatma Gandhi?",
      "options": [
        "Sarvodaya",
        "Satyagraha",
        "Karmabhoomi",
        "Bhogabhumi"
      ],
      "answer": "Bhogabhumi"
    },
    {
      "question": "Ambedkar's criticism of Mahatma Gandhi was based on Gandhiji's views on",
      "options": [
        "Varnashrama Dharma",
        "Sarvodaya",
        "Swaraj",
        "Ahimsa"
      ],
      "answer": "Varnashrama Dharma"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who among the following thinkers believed that the necessity of ends and means was to attain ends and ends justify means contrary to Mahatma Gandhi's ideas on means and ends relationships?",
      "options": [
        "Aurobindo Ghosh",
        "Raja Rammohan Roy",
        "Bal Gangadhar Tilak",
        "Rabindranath Tagore"
      ],
      "answer": "Bal Gangadhar Tilak"
    },
     {
      "question": "With whom did Mahatma Gandhi sign the Poona Pact?",
      "options": [
        "Jawaharlal Nehru",
        "B.R. Ambedkar",
        "Swami Vivekananda",
        "Sarojini Naidu"
      ],
      "answer": "B.R. Ambedkar"
    },
    {
      "question": "Mahatma Gandhi was critical of which of the followings?",
      "options": [
        "Ramrajya",
        "Village life",
        "Varnashrama dharma",
        "Modern civilization of the West"
      ],
      "answer": "Modern civilization of the West"
    }
  ,
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following sentences is not correct about the religious and political thought of Muhammad Iqbal?",
      "options": [
        "He emphasized on the self and human spirit",
        "He emphasized on the capacity for self determination",
        "He did not emphasize on the self within a community",
        "He emphasized on the self at the service of divine"
      ],
      "answer": "He did not emphasize on the self within a community"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who among the following thinkers has divided Iqbal's works into three domains 'world of india', 'of islam' and 'of Western thought'?",
      "options": [
        "Hermann Hesse",
        "Hegel",
        "Rousseau",
        "Marx"
      ],
      "answer": "Hermann Hesse"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following sentences is not correct about Iqbal's views on Islam?",
      "options": [
        "In Reconstruction of Religious Thought in Islam, Iqbal argues that Islam was experiencing stagnation for centuries that has left it behind other traditions",
        "He spoke about the need for reconstruction of Islam without breaking away from the past",
        "He insisted on Ijtihad which is about independent judgements or interpretations of Islamic laws",
        "He never considered that reformations of Islam was required for the moral regeneration of man"
      ],
      "answer": "He never considered that reformations of Islam was required for the moral regeneration of man"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following sentences is not correct about Iqbal's views on Sufism?",
      "options": [
        "He accepted the teachings of Sufism because it focused on the role of intuitions in the cognitive processes",
        "He did not reject the negative role of Sufis towards rationalistic philosophy",
        "He believed that mysticism of Sufis could not bring overall development of human beings",
        "He was critical of Sufis preaching of man's withdrawal from the real world"
      ],
      "answer": "He believed that mysticism of Sufis could not bring overall development of human beings"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following best describes the meaning of the term 'Khudi' as described by Iqbal?",
      "options": [
        "Self-Affirmation or ego",
        "Respect",
        "Morality",
        "Ethics"
      ],
      "answer": "Self-Affirmation or ego"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to Muhammad Iqbal the term 'Millat' refers to",
      "options": [
        "Individual",
        "Nation",
        "Religious community",
        "Nationality"
      ],
      "answer": "Religious community"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following sentences is not correct about Iqbal's views on Nationalism?",
      "options": [
        "His critique of the nation-state and call for the political re-organization of India were to relocate nation along the lines of religion",
        "His reformulation of the concept of nation and nationalism should not be understood as re-assertion of Pan-Islamism",
        "He did not view nationalism as a threat to the principles of Islam",
        "He described western civilization and 'nationhood' as 'narcotics of imperialism'"
      ],
      "answer": "He did not view nationalism as a threat to the principles of Islam"
    },
    {
      "question": "In Iqbal's religious and political thought term 'Qawm' refers to",
      "options": [
        "National community",
        "Religious community",
        "Enemy",
        "Society"
      ],
      "answer": "National community"
    },
    {
      "question": "Iqbal was associated to which of the following organizations during the freedom struggles in India?",
      "options": [
        "Hindu Mahasabha",
        "Muslim League",
        "Brahmo Samaj",
        "Indian National Congress"
      ],
      "answer": "Muslim League"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following texts is not a work by Iqbal?",
      "options": [
        "Khuftagan-i-Khak Say Istaghfar (A Land Asleep)",
        "Taswir-e-Dard (Portrait of Anguish)",
        "The Development of Metaphysics in Persia",
        "Mirat-ul-Akbar"
      ],
      "answer": "Mirat-ul-Akbar"
    }
  ,
    {
      "question": "Who among the following had inspired V D Savarkar's thinking on nation and nationalism?",
      "options": [
        "Vivekananda",
        "Raja Rammohan Roy",
        "Mazzini",
        "Rabindranath Tagore"
      ],
      "answer": "Mazzini"
    },
    {
      "question": "VD Savarkar was associated with which one the following organizations?",
      "options": [
        "Brahmo Samaj",
        "Abhinav Bharat Society",
        "Moderate section of congress",
        "Muslim League"
      ],
      "answer": "Abhinav Bharat Society"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following books is authored by VD Savarkar?",
      "options": [
        "The Indian War of Independence",
        "Arthashastra",
        "Gitanjali",
        "The Development of Metaphysics in Persia"
      ],
      "answer": "The Indian War of Independence"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following sentences is not correct about Savarkar's political thought?",
      "options": [
        "He glorified the Hindu rulers of the past",
        "He was inspired by Shivaji, who according to him represented the rise of Swadharma and Swaraj",
        "He was opposed to the militant methods of protest in the 1857 mutiny",
        "He believed in relative morality"
      ],
      "answer": "He was opposed to the militant methods of protest in the 1857 mutiny"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following sentences is not correct about Savarkar's views on Hindutva?",
      "options": [
        "He provided a theoretical basis for Hindu Rashtra in his major work Essentials of Hindutva, 1923",
        "He did not relate Hindutva to Indian nationhood",
        "For him, Hindutva is not a word but a history.",
        "Not just religion such as Hinduism but a history in full",
        "He was not primarily concerned with any particular theocratic or religious dogma or creed"
      ],
      "answer": "He did not relate Hindutva to Indian nationhood"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following languages did Savarkar believe would preserve Hindu culture?",
      "options": [
        "Hindi",
        "Maithili",
        "Marathi",
        "Sanskrit"
      ],
      "answer": "Sanskrit"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to Savarkar which one among the following is not the correct criterion of Hindutva?",
      "options": [
        "Language",
        "Common laws",
        "Rationality",
        "Common rituals"
      ],
      "answer": "Rationality"
    },
    {
      "question": "With which one among the following thinkers did Savarkar have serious differences?",
      "options": [
        "Rabindranath Tagore",
        "Mahatma Gandhi",
        "Aurobindo",
        "Raja Rammohan Roy"
      ],
      "answer": "Mahatma Gandhi"
    },
    {
      "question": "In which one of the following books did Savarkar critically examine the question of what constitutes a Hindu?",
      "options": [
        "The Essentials of Hindutva",
        "The Indian War of Independence",
        "Six Glorious Epochs of Indian History",
        "Hindu Pad-Padshah"
      ],
      "answer": "The Essentials of Hindutva"
    },
    {
      "question": "Savarkar defined Hindus in terms of three essential features. Which one among the following is not part of such features?",
      "options": [
        "As a nation (Rashtra)",
        "As a race (Jati)",
        "As a religion (Dharma)",
        "As a civilization (Sanskriti)"
      ],
      "answer": "As a religion (Dharma)"
    }
  ,
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following texts is not written by Rabindranath Tagore?",
      "options": [
        "Gitanjali",
        "Gora",
        "Ghare-Baire",
        "Anand Math"
      ],
      "answer": "Anand Math"
    },
    {
      "question": "Rabindranath Tagore renounced his knighthood in response to",
      "options": [
        "Battle of Plassey",
        "Jallianwala Bagh Massacre",
        "Non-Cooperation Movement",
        "Simon Commission"
      ],
      "answer": "Jallianwala Bagh Massacre"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following statements is not correct about Rabindranath's views on Zamindari system?",
      "options": [
        "As a practitioner of zamindari, he could sense the cruelty associated with the zamindari system",
        "He was genuinely apologetic and embarrassed about the whole system of zamindari",
        "He did not dissociate himself with the system of zamindari",
        "He believed that zamindari system which claimed to represent the interests of the people was flawed."
      ],
      "answer": "He did not dissociate himself with the system of zamindari"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to Tagore the real problem of India is",
      "options": [
        "Only political",
        "Mainly social",
        "Both social and political",
        "None of the above"
      ],
      "answer": "Mainly social"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who among the following thinkers defines nationalism as 'an imagined political community'?",
      "options": [
        "Rabindranath Tagore",
        "Lukacs",
        "Max Weber",
        "Benedict Anderson"
      ],
      "answer": "Benedict Anderson"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following sentences is not correct about Rabindranath's views on Nationalism?",
      "options": [
        "He considered the presence of specific challenges faced by India in developing its national self-consciousness",
        "He wanted India to develop a national self-consciousness grounded in the Indian cultural sensibility",
        "He believed that India can develop its own national self-consciousness by imitating or accumulating ideas present in modern western texts.",
        "He wanted these ideas of nation, nationalism to be grounded in the social."
      ],
      "answer": "He believed that India can develop its own national self-consciousness by imitating or accumulating ideas present in modern western texts."
    },
    {
      "question": "Tagore can also be regarded as a noted cosmopolitan thinker. Because",
      "options": [
        "He respected Indian tradition",
        "He believed in universal values of the West",
        "He respected the variety of traditions and nationalities, but also believed in the universal values",
        "He believed in the universal values of the East only"
      ],
      "answer": "He respected the variety of traditions and nationalities, but also believed in the universal values"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following sentences is not correct about Rabindranath's views on idea of man?",
      "options": [
        "He emphasized on both the moral and the spiritual aspects of human nature",
        "He did not believe in the moral or ethical side of man",
        "He was too radical in his understanding of man and individual freedom",
        "He also spoke about the dual nature or duality in man's nature"
      ],
      "answer": "He did not believe in the moral or ethical side of man"
    },
    {
      "question": "Tagore was not in favour of Gandhi's Satyagraha because",
      "options": [
        "For him it was not a practical idea",
        "It was being misused by some of the followers of Gandhi to promote bigotry",
        "He thought that Satyagraha alone could not bring about independence",
        "None of the above"
      ],
      "answer": "It was being misused by some of the followers of Gandhi to promote bigotry"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who among the following modern Indian thinkers developed the idea of 'oceanic circle'?",
      "options": [
        "Pt. Jawaharlal Nehru",
        "Raja Rammohan Roy",
        "Mahatma Gandhi",
        "Rabindranath Tagore"
      ],
      "answer": "Mahatma Gandhi"
    }
  ,
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following sentences is not correct about Aurobindo's political thought?",
      "options": [
        "For Aurobindo, nation was mother which he worshipped as divine",
        "For him, the struggle for nation and nationhood is not just about attainment of political freedom",
        "He did not believe in the attainment of a spiritual life or self",
        "His engagement with swadeshi or other revolutionary political activities was guided by his understanding of nation as a mother"
      ],
      "answer": "He did not believe in the attainment of a spiritual life or self"
    },
    {
      "question": "Aurobindo was convicted and jailed for one year in which of the following events?",
      "options": [
        "Alipore bomb case",
        "Jallianwala Bagh Massacre",
        "Non-cooperation movement",
        "Quit India movement"
      ],
      "answer": "Alipore bomb case"
    },
    {
      "question": "During the freedom struggle in India, Aurobindo was associated with which one of the followings groups?",
      "options": [
        "Moderate section of the Congress",
        "Extremists section of the Congress",
        "Azad Hind Fauj",
        "Satyagraha movement of Gandhiji"
      ],
      "answer": "Extremists section of the Congress"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following texts is written by Aurobindo?",
      "options": [
        "The Ideal of Human Unity",
        "Gitanjali",
        "Hind Swaraj",
        "Samvad Kaumudi"
      ],
      "answer": "The Ideal of Human Unity"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following sentences is not correct about Aurobindo's thought on self?",
      "options": [
        "Ego is present in all beings and it is not the self",
        "There is only one self which pervades in everyone",
        "The soul in each self is the portion of universal divinity which he calls Virat Purusha or supreme-being",
        "For him, the fulfillment of individual life is the utmost development of his egoistic intellect, or emotional cravings"
      ],
      "answer": "For him, the fulfillment of individual life is the utmost development of his egoistic intellect, or emotional cravings"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following signifies the true self as defined by Aurobindo?",
      "options": [
        "Ego",
        "Rational mind",
        "Spiritual individual or Virat Purusha",
        "Physical self"
      ],
      "answer": "Spiritual individual or Virat Purusha"
    },
      {
      "question": "Which one among the following sentences is not corect about Aurobindo's views on Nationalism?",
      "options": [
        "Aurobindo envisioned nationalism merely as a political programme",
        "He had a religious conception of nationalism",
        "He believed nationalism as a religion gifted by god and argued that god is immortal and so is nationalism",
        "He believed that nationalism can contribute in the larger human unity"
      ],
      "answer": "Aurobindo envisioned nationalism merely as a political programme"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following journals was published by Aurobindo?",
      "options": [
        "Samvad Kaumudi",
        "Karmayogin",
        "Kesari",
        "Mook Nayak"
      ],
      "answer": "Karmayogin"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following sentences is not correct about Aurobindo's views on Gita?",
      "options": [
        "He argued that the text should not to be understood in its metaphysical connotations of ancient times",
        "He argued that Gita should be understood in its renewed relevance of living truths that it contains",
        "His interpretations or essays on Gita was more future oriented rather than reverting to or reviving the past",
        "He did not believe that Gita could be a way to discover the future horizons"
      ],
      "answer": "He did not believe that Gita could be a way to discover the future horizons"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following characteristic is represented by Tamas as described by Aurobindo?",
      "options": [
        "State of ignorance",
         "The will to action",
        "The will to discover the truth of oneself and the world",
        "Karma yoga"
      ],
      "answer": "State of ignorance"
    }
  ,
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following sentences is correct about modern Indian political thought?",
      "options": [
        "It emerged merely as an Indian response to western challenges",
        "It is a decisive break from the ancient and medieval Indian past",
        "It emerged in the context of colonialism and formation of nation-state in modern India",
        "There was hardly any difference among the modern Indian political thinkers about the 'idea of India'"
      ],
      "answer": "It emerged in the context of colonialism and formation of nation-state in modern India"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following is a more appropriate method to study modern Indian political thought in contemporary times?",
      "options": [
        "Thinker centric approach",
        "Thematic approach",
        "Contemplative approach",
        "Traditional or conventional approach"
      ],
      "answer": "Thematic approach"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following sentences is not correct?",
      "options": [
        "Modern Indian political thinkers did not differ from their Western counterpart in terms of their metaphysical and epistemological assumptions",
        "Modern Indian political thinkers differed from their Western counterpart in terms of their metaphysical and epistemological assumptions",
        "They emphasized more upon synthesis rather than binaries",
        "Most of the political thinkers in modern India were deeply involved in the politics of their times"
      ],
      "answer": "Modern Indian political thinkers did not differ from their Western counterpart in terms of their metaphysical and epistemological assumptions"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who among the following is regarded as the father of modern Indian political thought?",
      "options": [
        "Jawaharlal Nehru",
        "Ambedkar",
        "Raja Rammohan Roy",
        "Ishwar Chandra Vidyasagar"
      ],
      "answer": "Raja Rammohan Roy"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following sentences is not correct?",
      "options": [
        "Raja Rammohan Roy emphasized upon the good practices and worthy ideas of Indian intellectual traditions.",
        "He was uncritical of the evil or irrational practices in Hinduism.",
        "He argued in favour of Western ideals for education.",
        "He supported the freedom of press during colonial times."
      ],
      "answer": "He was uncritical of the evil or irrational practices in Hinduism."
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following texts is not written by Raja Rammohan Roy?",
      "options": [
        "Tuhfat-ul-Muwahhiddin",
        "Samvad Kaumudi",
        "Mirat-ul-Akhbar",
        "Hind Swaraj"
      ],
      "answer": "Hind Swaraj"
    },
    {
      "question": "Raja Rammohan Roy's Persian text Tuhfat-ul-Muwahhiddin is translated into English as",
      "options": [
        "A Gift to Theist",
        "A Gift to Atheists",
        "A Gift to Deists",
        "None of the Above"
      ],
      "answer": "A Gift to Deists"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following sentences is not correct about the Brahmo Samaj?",
      "options": [
        "It was formed by Raja Rammohan Ray in 1828",
        "It fought against the practice of idol worshiping",
        "It stood for scriptures",
        "It fought against the ritual practices"
      ],
      "answer": "It stood for scriptures"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following sentences is not correct about Raja Rammohan Roy?",
      "options": [
        "He supported the new system of education started by the Britishers.",
        "He was not an ardent supporter of modern liberal education in colonial India.",
        "He wanted Britishers to employ English gentlemen to instruct the natives of India in mathematics, philosophy, chemistry, anatomy.",
        "He wanted to promote modern scientific liberal education because of their practical values and necessity"
      ],
      "answer": "He was not an ardent supporter of modern liberal education in colonial India."
    },
    {
      "question": "Raja Rammohan Roy undertook the task of translating Sanskrit texts into vernacular language, because",
      "options": [
        "Many of his contemporaries had already started translation of Sanskrit texts into vernacular",
        "He personally liked vernacular languages over Sanskrit",
        "The Government had asked him to do so",
        "He thought that it would end the monopoly of Brahmins over the sacred texts"
      ],
      "answer": "He thought that it would end the monopoly of Brahmins over the sacred texts"
    }
  ,
    {
      "question": "Who among the following was the spintual guru of Vivekananda?",
      "options": [
        "Shri Ramakrishna",
        "Raja Rammohan Roy",
        "Aurobindo Ghosh",
        "Mahatma Gandhi"
      ],
      "answer": "Shri Ramakrishna"
    },
    {
      "question": "Where did Vivekananda deliver his famous speech on universal tolerance?",
      "options": [
        "Indian Parliament",
        "World Parliament of Religion, Chicago",
        "Belur math",
        "Brahmo Samaj"
      ],
      "answer": "World Parliament of Religion, Chicago"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following sentences is not correct about Vivekananda's political thought?",
      "options": [
        "For Vhiekananda, the task was to reinterpret Hinduism and distance it from dogmas, irrational beliefs and rituals",
        "He focused on Advaita Vendants which believed in one supreme truth or Brahma and we are all manifestations of that",
        "In his views, men were different from reality or god",
        "He argued that Advaita Vedanta was meant for millions and not just for a priestly class"
      ],
      "answer": "In his views, men were different from reality or god"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following sentences is not comect about Vivekananda's views on education",
      "options": [
        "For him, education could revitalize the masses or give them hope and self-bellet in achieving something",
        "For him, the education was not just about memory or sccumulation of facts or information",
        "Education was to develop a holistic or a complete personality, for which he wanted a new positive education",
        "He never wanted the spiritual or religious teachings of East to be combined with the scientific or technological teachings of the West"
      ],
      "answer": "He never wanted the spiritual or religious teachings of East to be combined with the scientific or technological teachings of the West"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following sentences is not correct about Vivekananda's views on religion",
      "options": [
        "For Vivekananda, religion was not an end in itself",
        "For him, the goal of religion was human growth, social regeneration and harmony",
        "For him, religion is not a wider concept or universal in nature",
        "For him, religion was the basis of social, economic, poimcal, national and universal regeneration of self"
      ],
      "answer": "For him, religion is not a wider concept or universal in nature"
    },
    {
     "question": "Which one of the following statements is incorrect",
     "options": [
      "Vivekananda was not against caste system",
      "He was critical of the present distortions of the caste system",
      "According to him, the solution to the caste problem was to elevate all castes",
      "For him, social and political liberty could be realized without moral, ethical and religious grant"
     ],
     "answer": "For him, social and political liberty could be realized without moral, ethical and religious grant"
    },
    {
     "question": "Which among the following is not the characteristic feature of democracy as put forth by Vivekananda?",
     "options": [
      "By democracy, he meant a representative or indirect form of democracy",
      "Democracy for him is a man making process which inculcates faith, self-reliance and self-government",
      "He said democracy is a process which enables individual to realize his true self or true objectives in life",
      "His supreme faith in inalienability of freedom, equality and unity made him espouse democracy as a way of life"
     ],
     "answer": "By democracy, he meant a representative or indirect form of democracy"
    },
    {
     "question": "Who said that Vivekananda 'was not politician, he was greatest of nationalists'?",
     "options": [
      "Mahatma Gandhi",
      "Sister Nivedita",
      "Aurobindo Ghosh",
      "Rabindranath Tagore"
     ],
     "answer": "Sister Nivedita"
    },
    {
     "question": "Where did Vivekananda establish the headquarter of Ramakrishna mission or Belur math?",
     "options": [
      "Mumbai",
      "Hyderabad",
      "Jaipur",
      "Kolkata"
     ],
     "answer": "Kolkata"
    },
    {
     "question": "Vivekananda was associated with which one of the following groups?",
     "options": [
      "Sadharan Brahmo Samaj",
      "Christian Missionary",
      "Moderate section of Congress",
      "Extremists section of Congress"
     ],
     "answer": "Sadharan Brahmo Samaj"
    }
,
    {
        "question": "Which one among the following books was not written by Jawaharlal Nehru?",
        "options": [
            "Glimpses of World History",
            "Discovery of India",
            "Hind Swaraj",
            "An Autobiography"
        ],
        "answer": "Hind Swaraj"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which one among the following sentences is not correct regarding Nehru's views on socialism?",
        "options": [
            "Democracy and socialism are complementary to each other",
            "Socialism is meaningful only in the presence of individual freedom",
            "He added to the idea of socialism a moral concern",
            "He argued that socialism in India should be a blind imitation of the Western model"
        ],
        "answer": "He argued that socialism in India should be a blind imitation of the Western model"
    },
   {
        "question": "Nehru rejected the idea of 'Union of Democracies' propounded by which among the following theorists?",
        "options": [
            "Clarence K Streit",
            "Robert Michels",
            "James Samuel Goleman",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Clarence K Streit"
    },
    {
        "question": "Nehru was the founder editor of which of the following newspapers?",
        "options": [
            "Hindustan Times",
            "National Herald",
            "Times of India",
            "Mook Nayak"
        ],
        "answer": "National Herald"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which one among the following sentences is not correct regarding Nehru's views on religion?",
        "options": [
            "His general outlook towards life was guided by religious beliefs and practices",
            "He was skeptical towards all forms of organized religion",
            "His rational and scientific temperament prevented him to follow any religious dogmas and superstitions",
            "His secular spirit inspired him to establish a secular society"
        ],
        "answer": "His general outlook towards life was guided by religious beliefs and practices"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which one among the following sentences is not correct about Nehru's views on secularism?",
        "options": [
            "His secular philosophy was based on neither irreligiosity nor just material well-being",
            "For him secularism was not about granting equal status to all religions",
            "For him no religion should have special privileges",
            "For him no community should be deprived of their legitimate rights on the basis of religion"
        ],
        "answer": "For him secularism was not about granting equal status to all religions"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which one among the followings is not part of essential features of secularism as argued by Nehru?",
        "options": [
            "Neutrality in religious matters",
            "Equal status to all religions",
            "No harmony and fellow feelings among different religions",
            "Secularization of all areas of life"
        ],
        "answer": "No harmony and fellow feelings among different religions"
    },
    {
        "question": "Nehru had justified state intervention in which among the following areas?",
        "options": [
            "To counter the majoritarianism",
            "To assert the power of majority religious community",
            "To defend sectarianism",
            "To defend majoritarianism"
        ],
        "answer": "To counter the majoritarianism"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which one among the following sentences is not correct about Nehru's Discovery of India?",
        "options": [
            "Discovery of India was in many ways his own journey to understand and comprehend the timeless India",
            "He acquired a deeper appreciation of Indian history and philosophy",
            "His vision of India was based on religion and was not a secular democratic country",
            "He argued about scientific temper and objectivity"
        ],
        "answer": "His vision of India was based on religion and was not a secular democratic country"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which one among the following sentences is not correct about Nehru's views on liberal democracy?",
        "options": [
            "He envisioned India as a liberal democratic country both in principle and in practice",
            "For him democracy is not essential for both the individuals and society",
            "His conception of democracy was also related to the notion of equality",
            "His understanding of democracy had both economic as well as social freedom"
        ],
        "answer": "For him democracy is not essential for both the individuals and society"
    }
,
    {
        "question": "Which one among the following is not referred to as a grammar of anarchy by BR Ambedkar?",
        "options": [
            "Political parties",
            "Satyagraha",
            "Civil disobedience",
            "Non-cooperation"
        ],
        "answer": "Political parties"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which one among the following sentences is not correct about Ambedkar's views on liberal democracies?",
        "options": [
            "He believed in the representative form of government, however, in his opinion democracy is more than just representation",
            "For him, democracy is primarily a mode of associated living and of conjoint communicated experience",
            "His concept of democracy is related to his idea of a good society",
            "He was critical of the proposition that democracy is the medium of social transformations and human progress"
        ],
        "answer": "He was critical of the proposition that democracy is the medium of social transformations and human progress"
    },
    {
        "question": "According to Ambedkar preservation and strengthening of democracy require that it is guarded against three things. Which one among the following is not part of those three things?",
        "options": [
            "Extra-constitutional means of politics",
            "Partisan politics",
            "Hero worshipping",
            "Political democracy in the absence of social and economic democracy"
        ],
        "answer": "Partisan politics"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which among the following sentences is not correct regarding BR Ambedkar's conception of constitutional morality?",
        "options": [
            "It means being governed by the substantive morality of the constitution",
            "It refers to being governed by the conventions and protocols in the grey areas of decision-making process",
            "He argued that it is a natural tendency in human being and therefore does not require cultivation",
            "He criticized the use of political actions such as non-cooperation and satyagraha as conducive for constitutional morality."
        ],
        "answer": "He argued that it is a natural tendency in human being and therefore does not require cultivation"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who among the following scholars has argued about Ambedkar as 'the caste leader, an untouchable spokesman and a national statesman'?",
        "options": [
            "Eleanor Zelliot",
            "Karl Marx",
            "Mahatma Gandhi",
            "Jawaharlal Nehru"
        ],
        "answer": "Eleanor Zelliot"
    },
    {
        "question": "Ramabai is the author of which one of the following books?",
        "options": [
            "Gitanjali",
            "The High Caste Hindu Woman",
            "Ghare-Baire",
            "The Discovery of India"
        ],
        "answer": "The High Caste Hindu Woman"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which among the following sentences is not correct?",
        "options": [
            "Ramabai played an active role in reform movement and tirelessly worked for women's emancipation",
            "She opened two shelter homes—Sharade Sadan and Mukti Sadan for destitute women",
            "She never argued about liberating women through self-reliance",
            "While championing the cause of women, she transcended the limits of gender reforms set by the main reformers"
        ],
        "answer": "She never argued about liberating women through self-reliance"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which one among the following organizations was formed by Ramabai?",
        "options": [
            "Arya Mahila Samaj",
            "Arya Samaj",
            "Brahmo Samaj",
            "Buddhist Sangha"
        ],
        "answer": "Arya Mahila Samaj"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which one among the following sentences is not correct regarding Ramabai's views on religion?",
        "options": [
            "For her, religion did not mean any particular religious doctrine whether Hindu or Christianity",
            "She said true religion is conduct in accordance with one's conscience",
            "In her first book, Stree Dharma Niti (Morals for Women, 1882), Ramabai emphasized more upon Hindu religion and Hindu nation",
            "Religion for her was not a source of salvation"
        ],
        "answer": "Religion for her was not a source of salvation"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which University bestowed upon Ramabai the title of 'Pandita' (Women Scholar) and 'Saraswati' (Goddess of Learning)?",
        "options": [
            "University of Calcutta",
            "University of Punjab",
            "Cheltenham Female College, England",
            "University of Delhi"
        ],
        "answer": "University of Calcutta"
    }
,
    {
        "question": "Which one among the following sentences is not correct regarding Ramabai's views on gender?",
        "options": [
            "In her text, Stree Dharma Niti, Ramabai talks about the deplorable conditions of women in Hindu society",
            "She opposed child marriage and supported the idea that both men and women should choose their life partners",
            "She did not emphasize on the need of women's education",
            "She was however, not able to surpass the immediate gender roles ascribed upon women by society"
        ],
        "answer": "She did not emphasize on the need of women's education"
    },
    {
        "question": "According to Ramabai, Hindu sacred laws divide a Hindu women's life into three stages of life. Which one among the following is not in these stages?",
        "options": [
            "Childhood",
            "Married life",
            "Old age or widowhood",
            "Widow re-marriage"
        ],
        "answer": "Widow re-marriage"
    },
    {
        "question": "With whom Ramabai shared the view that there is no hymn in the Rig-Veda which suggests self-immolation of widows?",
        "options": [
            "Max Muller",
            "Raja Rammohan Roy",
            "Aurobindo",
            "Jyotiba Phule"
        ],
        "answer": "Max Muller"
    },
    {
        "question": "According to Ramabai which one among the following ways was not the correct way to uplift the conditions of marginalized upper caste Hindu woman?",
        "options": [
            "Self-reliance",
            "Education",
            "Forced marriage of Hindu women",
            "Native women teachers"
        ],
        "answer": "Forced marriage of Hindu women"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which one among the following books is an autobiographical account of Ramabai?",
        "options": [
            "A Testimony of Our Inexhaustible Treasure",
            "Stree Dharma Niti",
            "Gora",
            "Mook Nayak"
        ],
        "answer": "A Testimony of Our Inexhaustible Treasure"
    },
    {
        "question": "Rammanohar Lohia was affiliated to which of the following political parties during the freedom struggle?",
        "options": [
            "Communist Party of India",
            "Congress Socialist Party",
            "Akali Dal",
            "Hindu Mahasabha"
        ],
        "answer": "Congress Socialist Party"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following Indian languages did Rammanohar Lohia support to be recognized as the official language of India?",
        "options": [
            "Bengali",
            "Marathi",
            "Hindi",
            "Punjabi"
        ],
        "answer": "Hindi"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which one among the following is not the correct characteristic of a cosmopolite as mentioned by Rammanohar Lohia?",
        "options": [
            "A premature Universalist",
            "An imitator of superficial attainments of dominant civilizations",
            "An inhabitant of upper caste milieus without real contact with the people",
            "An irrational being"
        ],
        "answer": "An irrational being"
    },
    {
        "question": "Rammanohar Lohia sought the support of which among the following leaders to build a just society in 1950s?",
        "options": [
            "Jawaharlal Nehru",
            "Jayprakash Narayan",
            "BR Ambedkar",
            "L.K. Advani"
        ],
        "answer": "BR Ambedkar"
    },
    {
        "question": "Rammanohar Lohia was associated with which of the following Gandhian movements during the freedom struggle in India?",
        "options": [
            "Salt Satyagraha",
            "Non-Cooperation movement",
            "Civil Disobedience movement",
            "Quit India movement"
        ],
        "answer": "Quit India movement"
    }
,
    {
        "question": "Which among the following book was not written by Rammanohar Lohia?",
        "options": [
            "Caste System",
            "Fragments of a World Mind",
            "The High Caste Hindu Woman",
            "The Wheel of History"
        ],
        "answer": "The High Caste Hindu Woman"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which one among the following sentences is not correct about Lohia's views on caste?",
        "options": [
            "He supported violent anti-Brahminism, campaigned against Gandhi, constitution for fighting caste based discriminations",
            "He viewed caste as primary form of inequality existing in Indian society",
            "His approach to class and caste is different from the Marxists which mainly focuses on class",
            "He paid relatively greater emphasis on the gender based oppression along with caste"
        ],
        "answer": "He supported violent anti-Brahminism, campaigned against Gandhi, constitution for fighting caste based discriminations"
    },
    {
        "question": "In order to remove the oppressions of Indian women Lohia focused on the four way areas. Which one among the following is not one of them?",
        "options": [
            "Slavery of kitchen and the field of sanitation",
            "Forced marriage of women",
            "Re-examination of the institution of marriage",
            "Equality in education and property rights"
        ],
        "answer": "Forced marriage of women"
    },
    {
        "question": "Lohia's Presidential speech at Socialist Party convention in Panchmarhi, 1952 was famous for which of the following reasons?",
        "options": [
            "He spoke about capitalism",
            "He spoke about fascism",
            "He spoke about communism",
            "He spoke about a distinct brand of Indian Socialism independent of both communism and capitalism"
        ],
        "answer": "He spoke about a distinct brand of Indian Socialism independent of both communism and capitalism"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is not part of Lohia's conception of Sapt Kranti?",
        "options": [
            "For equality between man and woman",
            "Against political, economic and spiritual inequality based on colour and race",
            "Protection of social hierarchy based on caste",
            "Against arms, weapons and for satyagraha"
        ],
        "answer": "Protection of social hierarchy based on caste"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is not part of Lohia's conception of Chaukhamba Raj?",
        "options": [
            "Village",
            "District",
            "Province",
            "Capital"
        ],
        "answer": "Capital"
    },
    {
        "question": "To address the sensibilities and concerns of non-Hindi speakers, Rammanohar Lohia came up with a proposal. Which one among the following is not part of that proposal?",
        "options": [
            "He proposed Hindi as the official language of the central government with central government jobs reserved for non-Hindi speakers for a specific period",
            "He did not propose any group to abolish English both from internal and external communications",
            "He suggested a multi-lingual centre",
            "He proposed that a group of states could retain English to communicate with the central government"
        ],
        "answer": "He did not propose any group to abolish English both from internal and external communications"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is not correct about the study of modern Indian Political Thought?",
        "options": [
            "It helps us to understand and interpret modern Indian society and politics better",
            "It helps us to understand the history of India, its various ups and downs as interpreted by the men and women who helped them shape",
            "It helps us to understand the political ideas emerged in the colonial context as a response to orientalist thinking",
            "Modern Indian political thinkers did not have metaphysical and epistemological assumptions different from West"
        ],
        "answer": "Modern Indian political thinkers did not have metaphysical and epistemological assumptions different from West"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which one among the following is the movement proposed by Rammanohar Lohia?",
        "options": [
            "Tehri Dam movement",
            "Civil Disobedience",
            "Angrezi Hatao Andolan",
            "Narmada Bachao Andolan"
        ],
        "answer": "Angrezi Hatao Andolan"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who among the following thinkers was the proponent of Hindutva?",
        "options": [
            "Jawaharlal Nehru",
            "Mahatma Gandhi",
            "V.D. Savarkar",
            "Rammanohar Lohia"
        ],
        "answer": "V.D. Savarkar"
    }
,
    {
        "question": "Which one among the following sentences is not correct about Nehru's views on internationalism?",
        "options": [
            "He believed that nationalism and internationalism can co-exist and emphasized on maintaining a balance between the two",
            "He believed that it was internationalism and not merely nationalism which will be the unifying force in the future world",
            "For the wider interests of the international community, he preferred adjustments in national interests",
            "He argued that every nation can and should sustain and develop itself in isolation from each other"
        ],
        "answer": "He argued that every nation can and should sustain and develop itself in isolation from each other"
    },
    {
        "question": "Nehru signed the Panchsheel Agreement, 1954 with which of the following countries?",
        "options": [
            "Bhutan",
            "USA",
            "China",
            "Russia"
        ],
        "answer": "China"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which one among the following is not the correct feature of the Panchsheel Agreement?",
        "options": [
            "Aggression",
            "Peaceful co-existence",
            "Respecting sovereignty and territorial integrity",
            "Recognition of equality and mutual benefit"
        ],
        "answer": "Aggression"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which one among the following was not the ground for Nehru to oppose the idea of 'Union of Democracies'?",
        "options": [
            "It excluded countries like China and India",
            "It has limited itself to a few nations",
            "It did not include fascist nations",
            "He believed that without ruling out imperialism and colonialism no democratic union was possible"
        ],
        "answer": "It did not include fascist nations"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which one among the following sentences is not correct about Nehru's opposition to War?",
        "options": [
            "He advocated that war was negation of truth and humanity",
            "War not only leads to violence but also shackles the morality of the parties involved",
            "He advocated elimination of war as an instrument of foreign policy",
            "He did not believe that elimination of war is dependent upon elimination of the roots of war"
        ],
        "answer": "He did not believe that elimination of war is dependent upon elimination of the roots of war"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which one among the following sentences is not correct about Nehru's idea of world union?",
        "options": [
            "He believed that in the world union nations will enjoy autonomy in their internal matters",
            "In this world union nations will not have equal representation at global level",
            "It will be against imperialism, colonialism and racism",
            "It will be the perfect order of humanity"
        ],
        "answer": "In this world union nations will not have equal representation at global level"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which one among the following was not written by BR Ambedkar?",
        "options": [
            "National Dividend: A Historical and Analytical Study",
            "Caste in India: Their Mechanism, Genesis and Development",
            "India Wins Freedom",
            "The Problem of the Rupee"
        ],
        "answer": "India Wins Freedom"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which one of the following sentences is not correct about Ambedkar's activities on Dalit rights?",
        "options": [
            "He took opportunities provided by the British government to petition for political rights of the Dalits",
            "He formed the Independent Labour Party to fight elections",
            "He formed Scheduled Caste Federation, 1942 for uniting the untouchables in India",
            "He did not introduce the Hindu Code Bill"
        ],
        "answer": "He did not introduce the Hindu Code Bill"
    },
    {
        "question": "Ambedkar successfully negotiated with the British for the Dalit's rights in which of the following events?",
        "options": [
            "Communal or Ramsay MacDonald Award",
            "Round Table Conferences",
            "Poona Pact",
            "Simon Commission meeting"
        ],
        "answer": "Communal or Ramsay MacDonald Award"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which one among the following sentences is not correct about Ambedkar's views on caste?",
        "options": [
            "The Annihilation of Caste presents his views on caste",
            "In this text, he raised profound questions on the existence of caste system",
            "The prevalence of caste system made him criticize Hindu religion",
            "He did not believe that caste system was the governing principle of the Hindu society"
        ],
        "answer": "He did not believe that caste system was the governing principle of the Hindu society"
    }
]

